Mina Kirstein Curtiss Papers, 1913-2005
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
- SERIES III. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Friends and acquaintances
    - Levy, Harriet, 1941 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Lindbergh, Anne Morrow and other members of Morrow and Lindbergh families
      [See also SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL]
      - Anne Morrow Lindbergh to Mina Curtiss, 1929-85, undated (Box 13, Folder 1-8)
      - Mina Curtiss to Anne Morrow Lindbergh (photocopies), 1940 (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Typescript by Anne Morrow Lindbergh and related letter from Mina Curtiss, undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Constance Morrow Morgan, 1930-78, undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Anne Spencer Lindbergh, 1960 (Box 13, Folder 12)
      - Reeve Lindbergh Brown, 1983 (Box 13, Folder 13)
      - Mina Kirstein Curtiss Fund at Smith College
        - Executive correspondence, 1984, undated (Box 13, Folder 14)
        - General correspondence, A-Z, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 15-18)
    - Linscott, Robert (?), 1947 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - M, 1930-85, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Maloney, Daniel, 1977-78 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Marshall, Delia, 1977-85 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Martin-Chauffier, Louis, 1946-48 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - de Mornand, Louisa (includes fragments of writings), 1947 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Mortimer, Raymond, undated (Box 14)
    - Mencken, H.L. (photocopies), 1936 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Nathan, Robert, 1919-22, undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Neilson, Elizabeth, 1939, 1949 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Neilson, William Allan, 1919-45 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Nicolson, Marjorie, 1950-53 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Pope-Hennessey, John, 1962-79 (Box 14, Folder 12)
      [See also SERIES V. WRITINGS: Published works: Books: Other People's Letters, fan mail]
    - Proust, Suzy Mante, 1947-48 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - R, 1942, 1975 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Russian correspondents
      - Drapkina, Lucy, 1969-72, undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - Others, 1960-70, undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - S, 1939-84 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Sibilat, Magda, 1938-52, undated
      - Magda Sibilat (written by Pauline Nisbet on behalf of Sibilat, who was gravely ill), 1949-50 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Steegmuller, Francis, 1948-84, undated (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Storm, Hans Otto, 1940-41 (Box 15, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence about Hans Otto Storm, 1942, 1970-73 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - T, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Una [?], 1972-78 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Untermeyer, Louis, 1917-18 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Vecchi, Floriano, 1971, undated (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - W, 1976-85 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - Welles, Orson, undated (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - West, Rebeccca (includes photocopies and related correspondence), 1924-78 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Wilmerding, Gay, 1978-79 (Box 15, Folder 16)
    - Unidentified, 1981-85, undated (Box 15, Folder 17)
    - Stenographer's notebooks, Jan 1978-Jul 1983 (Box 15, Folder 18-23)
      - Aug 1983-Sep 1985 (Box 16, Folder 1-4)
  - Legal and financial
    - Pullman, Comley, Bradley and Reeves, 1978 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Ropes, Gray, Best, Coolidge and Rugg, 1952-60 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Ropes and Gray, 1961-74 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous: letter to the editor, The New Yorker, 1979 (Box 16, Folder 8)
- SERIES IV. TEACHING
  - Smith College
    - Grade book, undated (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - Teaching notes, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence from students, 1920s, 1977 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Clipping, Dec 1929 (Box 16, Folder 12)
- SERIES V. WRITINGS
  - Diaries
    - Journals, 1911, 1914, 1918-19 (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
    - Journal from trip to Cedar Rapids, Iowa, 1942 (Box 17, Folder 3-4)
  - Radio programs
    - Mercury Theatre of the Air
      - "War of the Worlds," clippings, 1938 (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Unidentified list, undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Listen, Iowa's Own Newspaper of the Air
      - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - Character profiles, 1942 (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - Scripts, 1942-43 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Answering Australia, scripts: 1943 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Answering You
      - Correspondence and listeners' surveys, 1943 (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - Scripts, #1-#8, 12, 1943 (Box 18, Folder 8-9)
      - Disc recordings, circa 1942 (Box 19)
        [See APPENDIX]
  - Published works
    - Lists of published works (incomplete), undated (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Statements of earnings from writings, 1965-71 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Books
      - Bizet and His World, 1958
        - Royalty statements, 1961-77 (Box 20, Folder 3)
        - Reviews, 1958-59, 1978 (Box 20, Folder 4)
        - Research materials: from Genevieve Bizet Straus: correspondence, printed material, clippings, transcribed excerpts, legal documents, and school records, circa 1883-1975 (Box 20, Folder 5-6)
        - Records of royalties on works by Georges Bizet, 1939-43 (Box 20, Folder 7)
        - List of documents about Georges Bizet held by Magda Sibilat, undated (Box 20, Folder 8)
      - A Forgotten Empress: Anna Ivanovich and Her Era, 1730-1740, 1974
        - Correspondence and contract, 1967-74 (Box 20, Folder 9)
        - Fan mail, 1974 (Box 20, Folder 10)
        - Royalty statements, 1976-78 (Box 20, Folder 11)
        - Reviews, 1974-75, undated (Box 20, Folder 12)
        - Research materials
          - Photographs, undated (Box 20, Folder 13)
            [See also OVERSIZE MATERIALS]
          - Catalogs, 1969, undated (Box 20, Folder 14)
        - Plates (Box 20)
      - Letters Home, 1944
        - Correspondence, 1944-72 (Box 21, Folder 1)
        - Research materials: typescripts of newspaper articles containing information about soldiers serving in World War II, 1942-43
          - Africa, Asia and Europe: Africa-Trinidad (Box 21, Folder 2-13)
          - United States:Alaska- Pennsylvania (Box 21, Folder 14-18)
          - Other, 1942-43, undated (Box 21, Folder 19)
        - Clippings, 1942-43 (Box 21, Folder 20)
        - Reviews, 1944 (Box 21, Folder 21)
        - Column in Cosmopolitan, "Letters Home"
          - Correspondence, galleys, clippings, 1944 (Box 21, Folder 22)
        - Radio program: What's Your Idea?
          - Correspondence and typescript, 1944 (Box 21, Folder 23)
      - Letters of Marcel Proust, 1949
        - Correspondence and copyright information, 1947-49, 1977 (Box 22, Folder 1)
        - Fan mail, 1949-50 (Box 22, Folder 2)
        - Royalty statements, 1967-78 (Box 22, Folder 3)
        - Reviews from U.S. publications, 1949-50 (Box 22, Folder 4)
        - Reviews from British publications, 1950-51 (Box 22, Folder 5)
        - Research material
          - Letters from Proust to Nahamas (photocopies), undated (Box 22, Folder 6)
          - Typescript, Proust and the Double 'I' of Two Characters by Andre du Bouchet, undated (Box 22, Folder 7)
        - Photographs
          - Marcel Proust, 1890-1922 (Box 22, Folder 8)
          - Marcel Proust with family and friends, undated (Box 22, Folder 9)
          - Other people, undated (Box 22, Folder 10)
          - Copy negatives, undated (Box 22, Folder 11-12)
        - Related material, 1956, undated (Box 22, Folder 13)
      - The Midst of Life, 1933
        - Correspondence, 1933 (Box 23, Folder 1)
        - Fan mail, 1928-53 (Box 23, Folder 2-5)
        - Typescript, undated (Box 23, Folder 6-7)
        - Serialized version, Atlantic Monthly, Jan-Apr, 1933 (Box 23, Folder 8)
        - Abridged version, Reader's Digest, Feb 1938 (Box 23, Folder 9)
        - Translation into French by Andre du Bouchet (incomplete), undated (Box 23, Folder 10)
        - Press releases and reviews, 1933 (Box 23, Folder 11)
        - Typescript, "background material," undated (Box 23, Folder 12)
      - Olive, Cypress and Palm: An Anthology of Love and Death, 1930
        - Correspondence and royalty statement, 1929-32 (Box 24, Folder 1)
        - Reviews, 1930 (Box 24, Folder 2)
      - Other People's Letters: A Memoir, 1978
        - Copy of reissued book, 2005 (Box 24)
        - Correspondence and contract, 1977-81 (Box 24, Folder 3)
        - Fan mail, 1978-84 (Box 24, Folder 4-5)
        - Royalty statements, 1978-84 (Box 24, Folder 6)
        - Research materials, undated (Box 24, Folder 7)
        - Typescript, Jun 1977 (Box 24, Folder 8-10)
        - Typescript, undated (Box 24, Folder 11-13)
        - Typescript (incomplete), undated (Box 25, Folder 1)
        - Photographs, 1890s, undated (Box 25, Folder 2)
        - Pre-publication correspondence and press releases, 1977-78 (Box 25, Folder 3)
        - Reviews from U.S. publications, 1978 (Box 25, Folder 4)
        - Reviews from British publications, 1978-79 (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Articles
      - Apollo
        - "Letters of Edouard Manet to His Wife During the Siege of Paris, 1870-71": published version, Jun 1981 (Box 26, Folder 1)
          - Typescripts, undated (Box 26, Folder 2-3)
          - Illustrations, undated (Box 26, Folder 4)
          - Correspondence, 1980-81 (Box 26, Folder 5)
      - Atlantic Monthly: "Harvard Calm and Henry Adams": published version and correspondence, 1920-21 (Box 26, Folder 6)
      - Boston Herald: Series of articles on the trial of Francis A. Carroll and Paul Dwyer for the murder of Dr. and Mrs. James Littlefield in South Paris, Maine
        - Notes, undated (Box 26, Folder 7)
        - Typescript, undated (Box 26, Folder 8)
        - Clippings of articles by Mina Curtiss, Aug 1938 (Box 26, Folder 9)
        - Clippings of articles by Arthur Stratton and others,1938-39 (Box 26, Folder 10-11)
        - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 26, Folder 12)
      - "A Mother's Career": clipping, 27 Aug 1939 (Box 26, Folder 12a)
      - Center: "Roma: Bizet's 'Souvenirs of Italy'": published version, Feb 1955 (Box 26, Folder 13)
      - The Cornhill: "Celeste": published version and typescript, Spring 1950, undated (Box 26, Folder 14)
      - German Encyclopedia of Music: "Georges Bizet": typescript, ca. 1966 (Box 26, Folder 15)
      - Harper's Bazaar: "Three Women": published version, Apr 1938 (Box 26, Folder 16)
      - High Fidelity: "The Ill-Starred Debut of the Girl From Arles": published version, Sep 1958 (Box 26, Folder 17)
      - History Today
        - Correspondence, 1968-78 (Box 26, Folder 18)
        - Typescript, "The Empress Anna Ivanova's Ice Palace, Jan 1973 (Box 26, Folder 19)
      - The Hound and Horn: "No Boswell": typescript, 1931 (Box 26, Folder 20)
      - Mademoiselle: Published version and correspondence,"The World We Wanted," Aug 1945 (Box 26, Folder 21)
      - Massachusetts Review
        - "Chosen?"
          - Correspondence, 1978-83 (Box 26, Folder 22)
          - Published version and typescript, Summer 1983, undated (Box 26, Folder 23)
          - Typescript, undated (Box 26, Folder 24)
        - "Some American Negroes in 19th Century Russia,"
          - Published version, Spring 1968 (Box 26, Folder 25)
          - Typescripts, n.d (Box 26, Folder 26-30)
        - "Manet Caricatures: Olympia," 1966
          - Correspondence, 1959-81 (Box 27, Folder 1)
          - Published versions, 1966 (Box 27, Folder 2)
          - Outline for proposed book, undated (Box 27, Folder 3)
          - Typescript, L'Exposition d'Edouard Manet by G. Randon (incomplete?), undated (Box 27, Folder 4)
          - Art work, undated (Box 27, Folder 5-6)
      - Musical Quarterly
        - "Unpublished Letters by Georges Bizet": published version,Jul 1950 (Box 27, Folder 7)
        - "Fromental Halevy": published version, Apr 1953 (Box 27, Folder 8)
        - "Gounod Before Faust": published version, undated (Box 27, Folder 9)
      - The Nation
        - "Cocktails": published version, Jan 1925 (Box 27, Folder 10)
      - New York Times, Op-Ed
        - "Women's Wasting Lives": published version, correspondence, clippings, May 1978 (Box 27, Folder 11)
      - Seven Arts Chronicle: "One of the Little Foxes": published version, correspondence, draft and notes, 1917 (Box 27, Folder 12)
      - Vogue
        - "A Letter at Last": published version, Jan 1945 (Box 27, Folder 13)
        - "The Midst of Life: The Curious Charm, The Free Satisfactions of Middle Age": published version, Oct 1945 (Box 27)
    - Book reviews
      - The Atlantic Monthly, 1933 (Box 27, Folder 14)
      - The Boston Herald, 1945 (Box 27, Folder 15)
      - The Living Age, 1936-37 (Box 27, Folder 16)
      - The Nation, 1925-70 (Box 27, Folder 17)
      - Washington Post
        - Correspondence, 1980-81, undated (Box 27, Folder 18)
        - Published versions and typescripts, 1981-82 (Box 27)
    - Translations by Mina K. Curtiss
      - My Friend Degas by Daniel Halevy, 1964
        - Typescript, undated (Box 27, Folder 19)
        - Research material, photographs, and reviews, 1963-66, undated (Box 27, Folder 20)
      - "Le Chat" by Jean-Louis Hue: draft, undated (Box 27, Folder 21)
      - "Letters to an Amazon," author unknown: draft, undated (Box 27, Folder 22)
      - Articles
        - Art News, Le Figaro Litteraire, and Vogue: "Chardin, or the Essence of Things" by Marcel Proust: (published versions in French and English, and typescript), 1964, undated (Box 27, Folder 23)
        - Mademoiselle: "Names and Places" by Marcel Proust:(published version in English), Oct 1956 (Box 27, Folder 24)
        - The Nation: "Love" by Tibor Dery: (published versions in French and English), Feb 1967, undated (Box 27, Folder 25)
        - The Virginia Quarterly: "Letters From China" by Alexis Leger (Saint-John Perse)
          - Published version, Autumn 1973 (Box 27, Folder 26)
          - Correspondence, 1973 (Box 27, Folder 27)
          - Typescript and fragments, 1973, undated (Box 27, Folder 28)
  - Unpublished works
    - M.A. Thesis: "Henry Adams and Failure": typescript, undated (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Books
      - As For Man
        - Correspondence, 1934-36 (Box 28, Folder 2)
        - Typescript, circa 1935 (Box 28, Folder 3-5)
      - The Past and I
        - Outline, undated (Box 28, Folder 6)
        - Original typescript, undated (Box 28, Folder 7-8)
        - Master typescript, undated (Box 28, Folder 9)
        - Master typescript, carbon, undated (Box 28, Folder 10)
        - Master typescript, second carbon (incomplete), undated (Box 28, Folder 11)
        - Typescript (incomplete), undated (Box 28, Folder 12)
        - Typescript, undated, edited by George Kirstein (incomplete) (Box 28, Folder 13)
      - Slices of Life
        - Draft, undated (Box 29, Folder 1)
        - Typescript, undated (Box 29, Folder 2-3)
        - Research materials
          - Harriet Lane Levy, correspondence, clipping, and typescripts, 1974, undated (Box 29, Folder 4-5)
      - Platon
        - Original typescript, undated (Box 29, Folder 6)
        - Original typescript, carbon, undated (Box 29, Folder 7)
        - Revised typescript, undated (Box 29, Folder 8)
        - Revised typescript (as orginally included in Slices of Life master typescript), 1985 (Box 29, Folder 9)
        - Revised typescript (as orginally included in Slices of Life master typescript), photocopy, 1985 (Box 29, Folder 10)
        - Revised typescript, 1985 (Box 30, Folder 1)
        - Typescript, cut versions, undated (Box 30, Folder 2-3)
        - Research notes, undated (Box 30, Folder 4-14)
      - Winter Letters
        - Correspondence, 1979-81 (Box 31, Folder 1)
        - Draft manuscript, undated (Box 31, Folder 2-3)
        - Original typescript, undated (Box 31, Folder 4)
        - Master typescript (incomplete?), undated (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts and typescripts
      - "Alamogordo Before the Bomb," undated (Box 31, Folder 6)
      - "Another Day," undated (Box 31, Folder 7)
      - "California Episode," undated (Box 31, Folder 8)
      - "Campanula Pyramidalis," undated (Box 31, Folder 9)
      - "The Desert" and "Desert Spring," undated (Box 31, Folder 10)
      - "Exercise in Narcissim," undated (Box 31, Folder 11)
      - "The Frontier, Bar," undated (Box 31, Folder 12)
      - "Giants and Pygmies," undated (Box 31, Folder 13)
      - "Lindbergh: A Personal Portrait," undated (Box 31, Folder 14)
      - "Military Intelligence, 1918 Style," n.d. (Box 31, Folder 15)
      - "A Monument," undated (Box 31, Folder 16)
      - "My [illegible] and Hopes," undated (Box 31, Folder 17)
      - "Natives," undated (Box 31, Folder 18)
      - "New Mexico," undated (Box 31, Folder 19)
      - "Period Piece," undated (Box 31, Folder 20)
      - "These Moderns," undated (Box 31, Folder 21)
      - Untitled, undated (Box 31, Folder 22)
      - Fragments, undated (Box 31, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence with publishers and literary agents
    - Al Hart (Fox Chase Agency)
      - Re: Other People's Letters, 1974-84, undated (Box 32, Folder 1)
      - Re: Slices of Life, 1979-85 (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Eakins Press, Houghton Mifflin and Random House, 1978-81 (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Research
    - Correspondence with Liliane Yacoel Ziegel, 1947-73 (Box 32, Folder 4-9)
    - Correspondence pertaining to Liliane Yacoel Ziegel, 1984-85 (Box 32, Folder 10)
    - Unidentified research material, undated (Box 32, Folder 11)
  - Writings by others
    - Lincoln Kirstein, undated (Box 32, Folder 12)
    - Lewis, Nell Battle, "The Follies of 1918 or How Doth the Busy Bolshevik (An Agitation in Two Spasms)," typescript, undated (Box 32, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous, 1937-77, undated (Box 32, Folder 14)
- SERIES VI. SUBJECT FILES
  - Saint-John Perse (Alexis Leger)
    - Writings
      - "Narrow Are the Vessels," 1937 (Box 33, Folder 1)
      - "Seamarks," 1937 (Box 33, Folder 2)
      - "A Selection of Works for Understanding World Affairs Since 1914", 1943 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Clippings, 1957-72 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - Murder cases: Elliott Speer murder, clippings, 1937 (Box 33, Folder 5)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - A Forgotten Empress: Anna Ivanovich and Her Era, 1730-1740, photographs, and plates (Map-case Flat file)
  - Letters Home, column in Cosmopolitan, "Letters Home," galley (Map-case Flat file)
  - Other People's Letters, review from Danbury New Times, 23 May 1978, containing photograph of Mina Curtiss (Map-case Flat file)
  - Letters of Marcel Proust, fold-out with photographs and letter (Map-case Flat file)
  - 2 photographs of Proton, undated (Map-case Flat file)
  - Certificate, Chevalier de la Legion d'Honneur 24 Feb 1960 (Map-case Flat file)